[GSA FEDSIM logo appears followed by text which reads "Introduction to the
Technical Evaluation Board." Chris Hamm,
FEDSIM director narrates.] Welcome to the
TEB also known as the Technical
Evaluation Board. As an evaluating member
of the TEB, there are a few things you
need to know. Your role is to evaluate
all proposals fairly and evenly and then
recommend the technically superior
proposal, which you'll accomplish by
reviewing the written technical part
first, then the oral presentations or the
video technical proposal. Of course, you
won't be on your own. The TEB consists of these voting members: a FEDSIM TEB chair,
an Assistant Acquisition Project Manager,
the FEDSIM project manager, and other
representatives from your agency. The TEB may also include technical advisors to
bring specialized knowledge to the
evaluation and observers who may observe
the process but will not provide ratings.
Only the voting members, the TEB Chair,
Assistant APM and client representatives
like you will evaluate proposals and
assign ratings. Many government entities
use different approaches to evaluation.
Some use a color rating scale. Others use
a mathematical evaluation approach to
reach an award decision. All
methodologies can be challenged in a
protest. Over time, FEDSIM has fine-tuned the evaluation
methodology to reduce risk and drive
quality outcomes.
That's why FEDSIM uses an adjectival
scheme for evaluating proposals.
Adjectival ratings differentiate the
technical qualitative differences that
can drive a best value award. This
approach adheres to the FAR and
distinguishes best quality, lowest risk
offers from the others. [On screen text
reads: "Preparing for evaluations"] To
prepare for the TEB evaluation, you
should read and understand the
solicitation and read the technical
evaluation plan to familiarize yourself
with the desired proposal qualities,
strengths, weaknesses, and deficiencies
and the adjectival ratings.
During the TEB training, your APM will
review this document in more detail.
The TEB's goal is to assign an adjectival
rating to each proposal. These ratings
will help identify the superior proposal.
To get there, you will first complete an
individual evaluation of the material
and presentations, documenting feedback
on the overall proposal while also
writing SWD statements against each
evaluation factor. Then you will convene
as a group to review the individual
evaluation statements to come to a
consensus on them. The TEB will assign
adjectival ratings for each proposal
factor and then assign an overall
proposal adjectival rating.
Once this is repeated for each proposal,
the APM documents the findings in the
TEB consensus report.
Some of these days
can get rather long, which is why FEDSIM
strives to make evaluations as fast and
efficient as possible. To help us do that,
delegate other client duties so that you
can focus on the evaluation.
Your TEB Chair will be in touch with you
about the required TEB training you need
prior to the start of the technical
evaluation. [End titles appear with the
GSA FEDSIM logo, which reads: "Introduction
to the Technical Evaluation Board."